A Guide to the Kurt Kehr Collection of Virginia Dialects, 1969-1994: SC 0206
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
- Series 3: Kurt Kehr Interviews D, March 1994-April 1994
  - 3-3: Smith, Edna, Leecy Bergton Yankey, Delmer Moyer, Jesse Hershberger, Stanley Moyer, Delmer Moyer, interviewed by Kurt Kehr and Sabine Wolters, April 4-8, 1994
    Side A: Interview with Edna Smith who is 81 years old. She married into the Smith family and her husband's mother spoke the Virginia German dialect, which they referred to as Dutch. Kehr reads some words in the Virginia German dialect to test her recognition of the words. Kehr also interviews a very old man (Delmer Moyer's father?) about his history in the area and who could or could not speak the Virginia German dialect. They are in Burgton and the man was a farmer for most of his life. This man tells stories from his life and the interview is entirely in English. They also interview 53–year-old Delmer Moyer. His father taught him how to speak the Virginia German dialect. Kehr asks him for the translation for multiple English words of common household items, counting, animals, and other words he remembers from his childhood. They discuss his various family members and which ones spoke the dialect. There is then an interview of 34-year-old Jesse Hershberger. Kehr reads him 40 sentences, which Hershberger then translates into his Virginia German dialect. Then Kehr asks for identification of basic words. Finally they run through his history in the area. For the remainder of the CD he tells a story about his past in the area in his Virginia German dialect. Side B: This contains an interview with 67-year-old Stanley Moyer. Kehr begins by reading English sentences and Moyer translates them to the dialect. Then Kehr lists some words in English and asks Moyer to provide the Virginia German word. This list includes grains, animals, plants, etc. Kehr also asks him to explain in dialect how he would plant and care for certain foods.
    - Original audiocassette, April 4-8, 1994 (Box 1, Audiocassette SC0206-CS-016)
    - Preservation master Side A, CD-R, April 4-8, 1994 (Box 1, Cd-r SC0206-OP-005)
    - Preservation master Side B, CD-R, April 4-8, 1994 (Box 1, Cd-r SC0206-OP-006)
  - 3-4: Beery, John, Grim Propst, interviewed by Kurt Kehr, April 10-12, 1994
    This recording contains an interview with John Beery who is 15 years old. John speaks the Virginia German dialect with his father. Kehr begins by reading sentences in English and asking John to translate them. Next Kehr asks him to identify individual words and numbers. Then Kehr asks him to explain in dialect his background and how he came to speak the dialect. He also asks about the use of the dialect in the community. Then Kehr asks Beery to identify the word in dialect for some of the items in the room. This CD also contains another interview with a man [Irvin Propst] and it begins with Kehr reading sentences in English, which the man repeats in his Virginia German dialect. He had interviewed this same man 20 years earlier, according to the CD. They discuss whether it was easier or harder and what difference 20 years has made in his speaking of the dialect. Kehr also has him count and identify some words in the dialect.
    - Original audiocassette, April 10-12, 1994 (Box 1, Audiocassette SC0206-CS-017)
    - Preservation master, CD-R, April 10-12, 1994 (Box 1, Cd-r SC0206-OP-007)
  - 3-5: Foltz, Hattie, Ollie Miller, John Dellinger, Glen Puffenbarger, John Stewart, interviewed by Kurt Kehr, April 14, 1994, April 17, 1994
    Side A: This recording contains an interview with Irvin Propst (who was born on July 1, 1926 in West Virginia) that begins with Kehr asking him for the translation of various English words. Kehr also asks the man to explain certain things in his dialect such as Groundhog's Day. Mr. Propst explains a little about his mother who taught him the dialect. They speak about different people in the community and their effect on and use of the dialect. Side B: This recording begins with an interview with Ollie Miller who is 78 years old. Sentences are read in English and Miller restates them in his Virginia German dialect. The voices are distorted in this recording, which makes it difficult to understand the interview after a while.
    - Original audiocassette, April 14, 1994, April 17, 1994 (Box 1, Audiocassette SC0206-CS-018)
    - Preservation master Side A, CD-R, April 14, 1994, April 17, 1994 (Box 1, Cd-r SC0206-OP-008)
    - Preservation master Side B, CD-R, April 14, 1994, April 17, 1994 (Box 1, Cd-r SC0206-OP-009)